yeah
hey everyone if I had to choose just one
topic that makes all of the others and
linear algebra start to click in which
too often goes unlearned the first time
a student takes linear algebra
it would be this one the idea of a
linear transformation and its relation
to matrices for this video I'm just
going to focus on what these
transformations look like in the case of
two dimensions and how they relate to
the idea of matrix vector multiplication
in particular I want to show you a way
to think about matrix vector
multiplication that doesn't rely on
memorization
to start let's just parse this term
linear transformation transformation is
essentially a fancy word for function
it's something that takes in inputs and
spits out an output for each one
specifically in the context of linear
algebra we like to think about
transformations that take in some vector
and spit out another vector
so why use the word transformation
instead of function if they mean the
same thing
well it's to be suggestive of a certain
way to visualize this input output
relation
you see a great way to understand
functions of vectors is to use movement
if a transformation takes some input
vector to some output vector we imagine
that input vector
moving over to the output vector then to
understand the transformation as a whole
we might imagine watching every possible
input vector
move over to its corresponding output
vector it gets really crowded to think
about all of the vectors all at once
each one is a narrow so as I mentioned
last video a nice trick is to
conceptualize each vector not as an
arrow
but as a single point the point where
its tip sets that way to think about a
transformation taking every possible
input vector to some output vector we
watch every point in space
moving to some other point in the case
of transformations in two dimensions to
get a better feel for the whole shape of
the transformation
I like to do this with all of the points
on an infinite grid
I also sometimes like to keep a copy of
the grid in the background
just to help keep track of where
everything ends up relative to where it
starts
the effect for various transformations
moving around all of the points in space
is you've got to admit beautiful
it gives the feeling of squishing and
morphing space itself as you can imagine
though arbitrary transformations can
look pretty complicated but luckily
linear algebra limits itself to a
special type of transformation ones that
are easier to understand called linear
transformations visually speaking a
transformation is linear
if it has two properties all mines must
remain lines without getting curved and
the origin must remain fixed in place
for example this right here would not be
a linear transformation since the lines
get all curvy and this one right here
although it keeps the line straight is
not a linear transformation because it
moves the origin this one here fixes the
origin and it might look like it keeps
line straight but that's just because
I'm only showing the horizontal and
vertical grid lines when you see what it
does to a diagonal line it becomes clear
that it's not at all linear since it
turns that line all curvy
in general you should think of linear
transformations as keeping grid lines
parallel and evenly spaced
some linear transformations are simple
to think about like rotations about the
origin
others are a little trickier to describe
with words
so how do you think you could describe
these transformations numerically if you
were say programming some animations to
make a video teaching the topic what
formula did you give the computer so
that if you give it the coordinates of a
vector it can give you the coordinates
of where that vector lands
it turns out that you only need to
record where the two basis vectors
I hat and Jay had each land and
everything else will follow from that
for example consider the vector V with
coordinates negative 12
meaning that it equals negative 1 times
I hat plus 2 times J hat
if we play some transformation and
follow where all three of these vectors
go
the property that grid lines remain
parallel and evenly spaced has a really
important consequence the place where
vlans will be negative 1 times the
vector where I had landed plus 2 times
the vector where Jay had landed in other
words it started off as a certain linear
combination of i had and J hat and it
ends up is that same linear combination
of where those two vectors landed
this means you can deduce where v must
go based only on where i had and J hat
each land
this is why I like keeping a copy of the
original grid in the background for the
transformation shown here we can read
off that I had lands on the coordinates
1 negative 2 and J hat lens on the x
axis over at the coordinates 30
this means that the vector represented
by negative 1 I hat plus 2 times J hat
ends up at negative 1 times the vector 1
negative 2 plus 2 times the vector 30
having that all together you can deduce
that it has to land on the vector 52
this is a good point to par
and ponder because it's pretty important
out given that i'm actually showing you
the full transformation
you could have just looked to see that V
has the coordinates 52 but the cool part
here is that this gives us a technique
to deduce where any vectors land so long
as we have a record of where i had and J
hat each land without needing to watch
the transformation itself
write the vector with more general
coordinates x and y and it will land on
x times the vector where I hat lands 1
negative 2
plus y times the vector where J hat
lands 30 carrying out that some you see
that it lands it
1 x + 3 y negative 2x plus 0y I give you
any vector and you can tell me where
that vector lens using this formula
what all of this is saying is that a two
dimensional linear transformation is
completely described by just four
numbers
the two coordinates for why I hat lands
and the two coordinates for where J hat
lands
isn't that cool
it's common to package these coordinates
into a two by two great of numbers
called a 2 by 2 matrix where you can
interpret the columns as the two special
vectors were i had and J hat each land
if you're given a 2 by 2 matrix
describing a linear transformation and
some specific vector and you want to
know where that linear transformation
takes that vector you can take the
coordinates of the vector multiply them
by the corresponding columns of the
matrix then add together what you get
this corresponds with the idea of adding
the scaled versions of our new basis
vectors
let's see what this looks like in the
most general case where your matrix
whose entries
ABCD and remember this matrix is just a
way of packaging the information needed
to describe a linear transformation
always remember to interpret that first
column AC as the place where the first
basis vector lands and that second
column B D is the place where the second
basis vector lands
when we apply this transformation to
some vector XY
what do you get
well it will be x times AC plus y x BD
putting this together you get a vector
ax plus B Y CX Plus D Y you can even
define this as matrix vector
multiplication
when you put the matrix on the left of
the vector like it's a function then you
could make high schoolers memorize this
without showing them the crucial part
that makes it feel intuitive
but isn't it more fun to think about
these columns as the transformed
versions of your basis vectors and to
think about the result is the
appropriate linear combination of those
vectors
let's practice described
being a few linear transformations with
matrices for example if we rotate all of
space 90 degrees counterclockwise
then I hat lands on the coordinates 0 1
I and J hat lens on the coordinates
negative 10
so the matrix we end up with his columns
0 1 negative 10
to figure out what happens to any vector
after a 90 degree rotation
you could just multiply its coordinates
by this matrix
here's a fun transformation with a
special name called a sheer in it
I had remains fixed so the first column
of the matrix is 10 but J hat moves over
to the coordinates 11 which become the
second column of the matrix and at the
risk of being redundant here figuring
out how a sheer transforms a given
vector comes down to multiplying this
matrix by that vector
let's say we want to go the other way
around starting with the matrix say with
columns 1 2 & 3 1 and we want to reduce
what its transformation looks like pause
and take a moment to see if you can
imagine it one way to do this is to
first move I hat - 12 then move J hat -
31 always moving the rest of space in
such a way that keeps grid lines
parallel and evenly spaced
if the vectors that I had and Jay had
land on are linearly dependent which if
you recall from last video means that
one is a scaled version of the other
it means that the linear transformation
squishes all of 2d space on to the line
where those two vectors it also known as
the one-dimensional span of those two
linearly dependent vectors
to sum up linear transformations our way
to move around space such the grid lines
remain parallel and evenly spaced and
such that the origin remains fixed
delightfully these transformations can
be described using only a handful of
numbers
the coordinates of where each basis
vector lands matrices give us a language
to describe these transformations where
the columns represent those coordinates
and matrix vector multiplication is just
a way to compute what that
transformation does to a given vector
the important takeaway here is that
every time you see a matrix you can
interpret it as a certain transformation
of space
once you really digest this idea you're
in a great position to understand linear
algebra deeply almost all of the topics
coming up from matrix multiplication to
determinant change of basis
eigenvalues all of these will become
easier to understand once you start
thinking about matrices as
transformations of space
most immediately in the next video I'll
be talking about multiplying two
matrices together
see them